<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: System Administration | Digital Magpie]]></title>
  <link href="http://ianp.org/categories/system-administration/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ianp.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-17T14:32:48+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://ianp.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ian Phillips]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quick Environment Setup]]></title>
    <link href="http://ianp.org/2014/11/17/quick-environment-setup"/>
    <updated>2014-11-17T14:32:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ianp.org/2014/11/17/quick-environment-setup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve recently had to set up and manage about a dozen Linux based virtual servers (not a huge number, but still) and it’s handly to have a separate user account on these machines that I can use to connect to for interactive use.  With that in mind here are a couple of quick tips for setting things up for a more pleasant experience with minimal fuss.</p>

<p>I like to use <a href="http://zsh.org">zsh</a> as my shell, but that’s easy enough to install via apt-get and so can be added to an automated build script. The fastest way to get a good configuration installed is via <a href="http://ohmyz.sh">Oh My Zsh!</a>, it uses the fairly horrible <code>curl | sh</code> installation style, so I don’t like to add it to an automated script, but it’s easy enough to check and run manually:</p>

<pre><code>$ curl -L http://install.ohmyz.sh | sh
</code></pre>

<p>The other thing is to get a decent <a href="http://vim.org">vim</a> setup, for this I use <a href="http://vim.spf13.com">SPF-13</a> which installs in a similar manner:</p>

<pre><code>$ curl http://j.mp/spf13-vim3 -L -o - | sh
</code></pre>

<p>Then I usually set up a couple of aliases based on what the machine will be used for, and I’m done.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Modest Proposal]]></title>
    <link href="http://ianp.org/2003/10/13/a-modest-proposal"/>
    <updated>2003-10-13T06:10:58+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ianp.org/2003/10/13/a-modest-proposal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.gnome.org/\~seth">Seth</a>: How about this (it was the first
thing that came to mind) - ‘Create a desktop operating system that
allows a single support operator to maintain 10,000 user wokstations.’
There are certainly huge implications for ease of administration and
scalability there, but probably even more so for ease of use. Hell, it’s
probably not even a realistic target, what with human nature and all.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
