<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: RvSnoop | Digital Magpie]]></title>
  <link href="http://ianp.github.com/ianpdotorg/categories/rvsnoop/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ianp.github.com/ianpdotorg/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-05T23:22:13+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://ianp.github.com/ianpdotorg/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ian Phillips]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jython 2.2b1 Released]]></title>
    <link href="http://ianp.github.com/ianpdotorg/2007/02/09/jython-22b1-released"/>
    <updated>2007-02-09T15:44:35+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ianp.github.com/ianpdotorg/2007/02/09/jython-22b1-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The first beta of Jython 2.2 has <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=12867&amp;package_id=12218&amp;release_id=485053">been released</a>! Jyhon scripting is
something that I’m planning to add to <a href="http://rvsnoop.org/">RvSnoop</a> so I’m quite
interested in this, especially given the current focus of development is
making the codebase easier to understand for new developers, I’ve looked
at it fairly recently and at the moment it’s quite a tangle!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RvSnoop 1.6.1]]></title>
    <link href="http://ianp.github.com/ianpdotorg/2006/12/26/rvsnoop-161"/>
    <updated>2006-12-26T04:38:10+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ianp.github.com/ianpdotorg/2006/12/26/rvsnoop-161</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A new stable build of <a href="http://rvsnoop.org/">RvSnoop</a> is available for <a href="http://downloads.sourceforge.net/rvsn00p/rvsnoop-1.6.1.tgz?download">downloading</a>
(it was actually released back on the 12th, but I forgot to post about
it here and have been away from the internet for a few days). New in
this release:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Added an option to republish records to different connections.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Added actions to export and import records to a binary file format (the records are stored in a ZIP based file, they are stored as wire format messages with some additional metadata).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Added an action to remove connections from the list; also, added some options to the connection list context menu to access the recent connections list.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Added a dialog to allow the user to configure different record types. The underlying code to support this was present in the 1.5 release, but there was no way to access it short of editing the saved project file by hand.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The build system no longer strips out unused classes from the included libraries. This increases the size of the download but in some cases the licenses of included libraries require this, and it simplifies the build process, which is a Good Thing.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Started to use the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/lang/">Commons Lang</a> and <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/io/">Commons IO</a> libraries from Apache instead of the utility classes that I had written myself. The next step is to start using <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/logging/">Commons Logging</a> instead of my own custom logger.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oh, Such a Good Infrastructure]]></title>
    <link href="http://ianp.github.com/ianpdotorg/2006/12/19/oh-such-a-good-infrastructure"/>
    <updated>2006-12-19T21:40:23+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ianp.github.com/ianpdotorg/2006/12/19/oh-such-a-good-infrastructure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Now that <a href="http://downloads.sourceforge.net/rvsn00p/rvsnoop-1.6.1-bin.tgz">the 1.6 release</a> of <a href="http://rvsnoop.org/">RvSnoop</a> is out of the door (OK, 1.6.1 ‘cause of a wart inthe original release), there are certain
features that I’d like to see added, and for the 2.0 release I want to
have in place a foundation that will make it easier to add these. A full
list of features can be found in the <a href="http://svn.sourceforge.net/viewvc/*checkout*/rvsn00p/trunk/rvsn00p/doc/plans.txt">plan file</a> in the <a href="http://sourceforge.net/svn/?group_id=63447">RvSnoop Subversion repository</a>, but some of the big ones that will impact
the overall architecture of RvSnoop are:</p>

<h3 id="pluggable-persistence">Pluggable Persistence</h3>

<p>Mechanism I’m going to migrate the record ledger to being persistent,
there are a couple of options here as to how this will be handled: flat
files, a combination of flat files and <a href="http://lucene.apache.org/java/">Lucene</a> based indexes, or
some kind of JDBC backed store.</p>

<p>One option would be to make the
persistence mechanism plug-able, this would also ease the use of an
all-in-memory storage system, like the one that is currently used (which
is useful when you just want to use RvSnoop as a graphical replacement
for <code>tibrvlisten</code>).</p>

<h3 id="able-to-run-headless">Able to Run Headless</h3>

<p>I’d like to add the
ability to run RvSnoop without the UI, this would be based on loading a
pre-configured project. Combining this feature with a JDBC backed store
this could be really useful for auditing and logging messages.</p>

<h3 id="ems-support">EMS Support</h3>

<p>I registered the <a href="http://emssnoop.org/">emssnoop.org</a> domain at the same time
as <a href="http://rvsnoop.org/">rvsnoop.org</a>, and there has been a project on SourceForge for a
while, even if it hasn’t had anything checked in to it yet! An open
question is whether to try for generic JMS support or just work with EMS
directly.</p>

<h3 id="user-written-plug-ins">User Written Plug-ins</h3>

<p>It would be nice to be able to
cleanly extend RvSnoop if required, without going back and modifying the
main code base.</p>

<h3 id="so-what-about-20">So, What About 2.0?</h3>

<p>All (well, most) of these
features point to a need for an extensible plug-in system,
<a href="http://www.eclipse.org/">Eclipse</a> has shown that a good way of architecting a desktop
application (or any application, for that matter) is to build it
entirely from plug-ins wrapped around a small core. So, the upshot of
this is that I’m planning on migrating to a managed runtime, probably
<a href="http://www.osgi.org/">OSGi</a>, for the 2.0 release. I’ll talk about this more in another
post. In particular, what’s the cost/benefit ratio of using this type of
runtime; and which runtimes are good?</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RvSnoop 356]]></title>
    <link href="http://ianp.github.com/ianpdotorg/2006/12/07/rvsnoop-356"/>
    <updated>2006-12-07T18:59:37+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ianp.github.com/ianpdotorg/2006/12/07/rvsnoop-356</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A new development build of <a href="http://rvsnoop.org/">RvSnoop</a> is available for
<a href="http://downloads.sourceforge.net/rvsn00p/rvsnoop-356-bin.tgz">downloading</a>. This release contains all of the features that will
be in the finished 1.6 release, due out sometime next week. Changes from
the last development build include:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Added support for republishing on different connections.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Added column to ledger to display wire size of messages.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Fixed bug that caused republished messages to be filtered incorrectly from the subject hierarchy.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Fixed bug with ledger renderer which caused striping to break when columns were added/removed from the view.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Minor code clean-ups and removal of a couple of unused methods.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Updated the FAQs page with correct details of timestamp formatting in ledger (this hasn’t been pushed out to the public site yet).</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>The only things left to do now (assuming no new bugs are found)
are some additional testing and documentation updates.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RvSnoop 353]]></title>
    <link href="http://ianp.github.com/ianpdotorg/2006/12/06/rvsnoop-353"/>
    <updated>2006-12-06T00:42:35+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ianp.github.com/ianpdotorg/2006/12/06/rvsnoop-353</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A new development version of <a href="http://rvsnoop.org/">RvSnoop</a> is now available for
<a href="http://downloads.sourceforge.net/rvsn00p/rvsnoop-353-bin.tgz">download</a>. This version adds:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Saving and restoring messages between sessions.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Remove Connection as a context sensitive menu option.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Improved drag and drop support.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>And also fixes some bugs
involving the screen menu on Mac OS X. The save and restore messages
option writes the selected records from the ledger to a ZIP based binary
file format (it’s the same format that is used internally by the copy
and paste mechanism). The format has also been enhanced to include
subject information for the messages, as this is stripped out by the raw
Rendezvous library calls.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
