<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: News | Digital Magpie]]></title>
  <link href="http://ianp.org/categories/news/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ianp.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-17T20:04:56+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://ianp.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ian Phillips]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[InfoQ Presentations]]></title>
    <link href="http://ianp.org/2008/07/31/infoq-presentations"/>
    <updated>2008-07-31T08:19:56+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ianp.org/2008/07/31/infoq-presentations</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> are one of my favourite tech information sites anyway and the
signal to noise ratio there is normally pretty high, they’ve got 3 great
new presentations out today:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>in <a href="http://www.infoq.com/news/2008/07/Developing-Expertise-Dave-Thomas">Herding Racehorses, Racing Sheep</a>, Dave Thomas talks about the problems of treating developers
as interchangeable cogs (or <em>fungible resources</em>, as the project
management crowd would say). Some great ideas for bringing new team
members up to speed quickly (about 18 minutes in);</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>in <a href="http://www.infoq.com/news/2008/07/presentation-botch-scalability">The Top 10 Ways to Botch Enterprise Java Scalability and Reliability</a>, Cameron
Purdy of Oracle talks about scaling Java. Obviously it’s not an
impartial view but his points are good ones and it’s an interesting
talk;</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>in <a href="http://www.infoq.com/articles/ddd-evolving-architecture">Domain-Driven Design in an Evolving Architecture</a>, Mat
Wall and Nik Silver talk about their experiences applying DDD at the
<a href="http://guardian.co.uk/">Guardian’s web site</a>, it covers why they selected DDD as a method as
well as the benefits that they feel it brought. I’ve heard them talk
about this before, on <a href="http://se-radio.net/">SE Radio</a>, and to be honest, it worked better
in that format I thought - the written version here needs to be edited
down to about half it’s current length;</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>finally, <a href="http://www.infoq.com/news/2008/07/Architecture-Reviews-Brock">Rebecca Wirfs-Brock talks about</a> the benefits of, and problems of conducting,
architectural reviews. I’ve listened to some of this before as Rebecca
did an <a href="http://www.se-radio.net/podcast/2008-04/episode-93-lessons-learned-architecture-reviews-rebecca-wirfsbrock">interview</a> with <a href="http://se-radio.net/">SE Radio</a> a while back, but this is good
for people who haven’t heard her talk before.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Maths at the BBC]]></title>
    <link href="http://ianp.org/2005/08/04/maths-at-the-bbc"/>
    <updated>2005-08-04T16:36:21+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ianp.org/2005/08/04/maths-at-the-bbc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As reported at the <a href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/technology/4745205.stm">BBC News</a> site, ‘One in
seven new mobiles faulty’, the opening line of the article is ‘An
estimated two million of the 18 million mobiles sold last year in the UK
could have been faulty’, so, clearly, elementary maths isn’t a
requirement for passing most media studies courses these days.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moron]]></title>
    <link href="http://ianp.org/2004/03/23/moron"/>
    <updated>2004-03-23T20:03:17+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ianp.org/2004/03/23/moron</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.nypost.com/news/nationalnews/21043.htm">New York Post</a>. All
I can say is: what… a… fucking… idiot. Next!</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> The NY Post page has been moved so the link above no longer works. Sorry.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
